<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The happy entraunce of the high borne Queene of Spaine, the Lady Margarit of Austria in the renovvned citty of Ferrara. With feastiuall ceremonies vsed by Pope Clement the eight, in the holy mariage of their Maiesties. As also in that of the high borne Archduke Albertus of Austria, with the infanta Isabella Clara eugenia, sister to the catholique King of Spaine, Phillip the third. First translated out of Italian after the coppy printed at Ferrara, allowed by the magistrates.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119688</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854895</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20351</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06892)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20351)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 478:11 or 1712:5b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The happy entraunce of the high borne Queene of Spaine, the Lady Margarit of Austria in the renovvned citty of Ferrara. With feastiuall ceremonies vsed by Pope Clement the eight, in the holy mariage of their Maiesties. As also in that of the high borne Archduke Albertus of Austria, with the infanta Isabella Clara eugenia, sister to the catholique King of Spaine, Phillip the third. First translated out of Italian after the coppy printed at Ferrara, allowed by the magistrates.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [J. Windet for] Iohn Woolfe, and are to be solde at his shop in Popes head Alley, neere to the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Item at 1712:5b is bound with: A Briefe and true declaration of the sicknes, last words, and death of the King of Spain, Phillip the Second of that name. Edinburgh : Printed by Robert Walde-graue, printer to the Kings Majestie, 1599.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in the Bodleian Library and the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Margarita, --  de Austria, Queen, consort of Philip III, King of Spain, 1584-1611.</term>
               <term>Albrecht --  VII, --  Archduke of Austria, 1559-1621.</term>
               <term>Isabel Clara Eugenia, --  Infanta of Spain, 1566-1633.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The happy entraunce of the high borne Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> Margarit <hi>of</hi> Auſtria, <hi>in the</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novvned Citty of Ferrara.</p>
            <p>With feaſtiuall ceremonies vſed by Pope Clement the eight, in the holy Mariage of their Maieſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo in that of the high borne Archduke</hi> Albertus of Auſtria, with the Infanta Iſabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Clara eugenia, Siſter to the Catholique King of Spaine, Phillip the third.</p>
            <p>Firſt tranſlated out of Italian after the Coppy printed at Ferrara, allowed by the Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Woolfe, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Popes head Alley, neere to the Exchange. 1599.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The happie entrance of the high <hi>borne Queene of Spaine, the</hi> Ladie Margarit of Auſtria, in the renowned Cittie of Ferrara.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the Thurſday at night, being the twelfe of the moneth of Nouember, came the high borne Quéene, Lady <hi>Margarit</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> on the Iland, a delightfull place, at the Bridge of darke <hi>Meyrs,</hi> nine miles from <hi>Ferrara,</hi> where ſhe was receiued, feaſted, and ſerued by the houſholde of the Pope. And the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row following, her Maieſtie was aduertiſed that at her pleaſure ſhe might come into the cittie of <hi>Ferrara:</hi> wherevpon was preſentlye replyed, that ſhe would repaire to the cittie at ten of the clocke, to which ende his Holineſſe ſent two Legates, which were the illuſtrious Cardinall <hi>Bandino,</hi> and the Cardinall of <hi>St. Clement,</hi> noblye accompanied by many Prelats and Gentlemen, and two bandes of Launces, and one of Carabins, and then the Coaches and Litters: all which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired in good and modeſt order to the ſaid Iland, where (after the dewe ceremonies of the Legates were ended) ſhe with her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Archeducheſſe, mounted in a coache prepared for them, followed with all their ſute and retinue, together with the high-borne Archeduke <hi>Alberto,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Gandia</hi> and <hi>Vmala,</hi> and the great Conſtable: the gouernour of <hi>Millain,</hi> the Embaſſador of Spaine, and the Prince <hi>Don Zanges, D. Maximillian Triſtiani,</hi> and a Germaine Princeſſe, with many other lords of name in coaches and Litters, and came thus in faire order towards the gate of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, where not farre from thence ſhe deſcended into a houſe made of purpoſe of Wood, richely beautified, with a Pauillion and a Chaire. There her Maieſtie ſtayed vntill the holye Colledge of Cardinals appeared, cloathed pontifically to receiue her, and to conduct her to the Palace with their traine. The ſaid Cardinals being come, and making a faire ſhew in turning, her Maieſtie had conference with the Cardinall <hi>De Medicis:</hi> after which ſhe was ſaluted of all the reſt, and taken betwéene the Cardinals, <hi>Sforra</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20351:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>Mont Alto:</hi> when comming to the Cittie gate, many péeces of ordinance were diſcharged. Vpon the ſaide gate on the outſide were painted thrée armes, to wit: thoſe of his Holineſſe in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, at the left hand the Quéenes, and at the right hand thoſe of the Catholique King, with this writing:</p>
            <q>Angelii gaudent, mortales exultant, Margaritam Auguſti ſanguinis pietatis virtutumque omnium ſplendore lucidiſſimam, ſimul laetiſſime excipiunt.</q>
            <p>Which is in Engliſh.</p>
            <q>The Angels reioyce, and mortall men make merrie and receiue with great ioye, <hi>Margarit</hi> of imperiall linage, adorned with the light of godlineſſe.</q>
            <p>Within the gate were likewiſe painted fiue armes, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the Popes: on the right hand thoſe of the King of Spaine and of the Archeduke <hi>Albertus,</hi> and on the left hand thoſe of the Quéene of Spaine, and of the high borne Infant, wife to the ſaid Archeduke <hi>Albertus,</hi> with theſe verſes vpon them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vrbem aduentus tui lumine illuſtratum</l>
               <l>Regina, redde tuo hoſpitio glorioſam.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In this ſorte came her Maieſtie happilye in, at eleuen of the clocke with a calme weather, in ſo much that it ſéemed that the heauen was cleered by her royall preſence: there appeared for her auantguarde (after that a number of Wagons and Carts, laden with ſundrye goods and bagadge were come in, alſo the coaches and Litters of hir Maieſtie, richly furniſhed and opened) two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Horſemen, the one being ſhot, and the other Launces, with their Trumpets in mourning apparrell, with blacke Flags at their Launces, which were the men of the great Conſtable of <hi>Millain.</hi> After theſe followeth a great number of Horſe of the court: after theſe followed two companies of Horſe of the Guarde of the Legate Cardinall <hi>Aldobrandino,</hi> the one company were ſhot, the other Launces: then came eight Trumpets and one in the middle, who played on two great Daniſh Kettel drums. After
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20351:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
theſe followeth the bagadges of the Cardinals, and then many Milaneſians and other Gentlemen, all mourning.</p>
            <p>Then followed the Mace bearers of the Cardinals, and the Mules, pontifically clothed in redde, and the Cardinals with Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Cappes, to the number of 19, to wit, <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orenza, Aſcoli, Montelpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, Boromeo, Camerino Orimontano, Bandino, S. Clement, Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio, Auila, Branchetto, Ceuara, Arrigone, Farneſe, Santiquatro, Aldobrandino,</hi> and <hi>Ceſis,</hi> with the Popes Guarde of Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers.</p>
            <p>There appeared the high borne Quéene in the middle, betwéene the Cardinals <hi>Sforza,</hi> and <hi>Mont Alto,</hi> with her guarde of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines clothed in blacke Veluet: her Maieſtie was on a white Palfrey, caparaſſoned with cloath of Siluer wrought with Gold, ſhe being apparelled in blacke with a blacke ſilke Cap, and a rich pleaſant head-tyre, which was open ſo that one could perceiue her faire haire, which reſembled threds of Gold. After her, came the high borne Archdutcheſſe her mother alſo on horſebacke, on a Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey couered with Peache colour Veluet, imbrodred with Golde. Theſe Palfreyes with their furniture, were ſent them by the Pope, on the left hand of the Archdutcheſſe, rode the Archduke <hi>Albert</hi> clothed in black. For the Réere guard, followed one compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Archers on horſe back, with péeces in their hands apparrelled in blacke, and after them came the lyght horſe men of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And laſtly followed an innumberable number of waggons, with Lordes, Gentlemen and Gentlewomen belonging to his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>In this order they came through the Angell ſtréete towarde the great Court, and being come to the pallace of the Embaſſadour of the Emperor, there was an vpper portall fairely painted and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with many garlands: in this portall was a woman holding a great baſe, on the which were foure armes, to wit: thoſe of his holineſſe, of the Emperour, of the King of Spaine, and of the archeduke <hi>Albertus,</hi> which were accompanied and defended by religion and Iuſtice, and from the heauen deſcended victory, who with her hand, pointed to the ſame Armes. Her Maieſty following on ſtill, and comming at the Cathedrall Church, ſhe paſſed through a triumphall Arke, ſet vp before the Court gate very coſtly, and vnderſet with foure Pillers, in the manner of that of <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> with an Image on each ſide, which in the right hand held a garland of Bayes with a role, wherein was the word <hi>Iugum.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20351:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And on the left hand alſo was a role wherein was Maritald in the Fronteſpire. <hi>Phillipo &amp; Margarite Auſtiacis, imperatorum glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, ſuaque pietate inclitis, vt Catholicorum Regum ſoboles propage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, matrimonio di vnitas coniunctis anni multi, liberorum topia, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petua felicitas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phillip</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> illuſtrous through the imperiall glory, and her owne Godlineſſe: to the end that the royall gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration might be delated, through the matrimoniall eſtate by God conioyned, God graunt long life, ſtore of Children, and a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall felicity.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Nichien</hi> were two Images with trumpets, the one ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifiyng Fame, in the vppermoſt, the armes of his holineſſe, in the middeſt on the right ſide, the King of Spaines, and on the other ſide the Queenes.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as ſhe was come into the Court, ſhe found a great paire of ſtayres builded of wood, with leaues, &amp; before on the baſe were the pictures of the holy Apoſtles <hi>S. Peter</hi> and <hi>S. Paul,</hi> where her Maieſty alighted, and went vp the ſaid ſtaires, betweene the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid two Cardinals: after her the Archduches her mother, with the Archduke, &amp; the reſt following, &amp; ſhe was conducted in a certaine Chamber, and from thence into the conſiſtory hall, where ſhe repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelfe, vntill (by the Lord <hi>Bernardin Scotto</hi> of <hi>Millan,</hi>) was ſpoken a ſhort but excellent and eloquent oration to his Holineſſe, who ſate in th' vpper end of the Hall, mounted in pontificall robes, and enuironed with his holy Colledge of Cardinals: at the ende of the oration, appeared the Quéene with her Mother, the Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke and her Court, with many burning Torches, and comming before his Holineſſe, knéeled all thrice downe, and then kiſſed his féete, firſt her Maieſty, after her her Mother, and then th' Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke, to the Quéene the Pope bowed himſelfe, giuing her his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, ſaying certaine words, and without other ceremonies he departed with the Cardinals.</p>
            <p>Her Maieſty departing went into the new Chambers, which were richly adorned, and eſpecially one (which the Pope had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of purpoſe to be made for her Maieſty) was rich, ſumptuous, and wonderfull, which if I ſhould deſcribe, theſe leaues would not ſuffice me. The Ladies and Gentlewomen of the Quéenes traine, were likewiſe all royally lodged in Chambers cloſe to the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her Maieſty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20351:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Satterday morning after that the Quéene had heard the Maſſe which was celebrated by his Holineſſe, together with the high borne Mother, &amp; the Archduke, they went to dinner with his Holineſſe, and the great Conſtable, ſerued her for Cup hearer, and when ſhe had drunke, th'Embaſſador of <hi>Spaine</hi> gaue her the Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, at night the Cardinall <hi>Aldobrandino</hi> ſupped with her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty.</p>
            <p>The Sunday Morning earlye, her Maieſtie appeared like a Bride, richely attired, and accompanied with the Cardinals <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe</hi> and <hi>Santiquatro,</hi> with all her retinue, appair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled in riche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and hir Germaine Guarde, cloathed in Silke and Veluet, red and yllow, alſo the horſemen with flags of Siluer, red and black.</p>
            <p>Being come into the Cathedrall Church, which was ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly hung and beautified, the mariage was ſolemnized, with ſuch ceremonies as were requiſite, her Maieſty was merried to the Archduke in the name of the Catholique King <hi>Phillip</hi> the thyrd. and the ſame Archduke married the Embaſſador of <hi>Spaine</hi> in the name of the Infanta of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the Lady <hi>Iſabella clara engenia,</hi> ſiſter to the King, whome he hath taken to wife.</p>
            <p>The ſame day after dinner; in token of pleaſure and ioy, were made many Maſkes, inſomuch that in the place <hi>Giudecca,</hi> were ſéene many Knights and Gentlewomen in maſkes, with ſo much people in the ſtréetes, that the Coatches could giue them no way, although they withdrew themſelues to the Caſtell walles, and they came vntill the Pallace of the Illuſtrous Dame Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſa:</hi> But her Maieſty came not there, becauſe that in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhe had receiued the holy Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The ſame night in the great Hall was held a ſumptuous Feaſt, to which came many Gentlewomen of <hi>Ferrara</hi> in Maſkes, very pleaſantly furniſhed and attyred: when comming vp the ſtayres, they were ſaluted by a great number of Trumpets and Drums: and in the Hall, by the muſicke of diuers ſwéete and delightfull ſoundes.</p>
            <p>On the Munday her Maieſty went to S. <hi>Maria del valdo</hi> to ſée the miraculous bloud, from thence to S. <hi>Vito,</hi> where ſhe heard a moſt ſwéet noyſe of muſike, of the honorable Lords there.</p>
            <p>Toward the Euening ſomewhat late, 30. Maides like Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimphs made an aſſay, for the next day to make a ſhip chaſe within the Caſtell wall with ſixe boates, and were apparrelled with ſcarffes in lyueries, fiue and fiue, to wit: Gréene and Red, Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20351:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Yellow and Blewe, White, White and Blewe, with theyr hayre and leathers of the ſame colour: ſome plaide on cimbals, and other ſinging made a pleaſant noiſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame day towards night, in the Hall of the Guarde of the Pope, in the Caſtell, was made a proofe of the play of <hi>Iudith</hi> and <hi>Holophernas</hi> in Latin, which the enſuing night was by the Ieſuit Schollers plaide before her Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Tewſday about 10. of the clocke the ſaid women made their ſhip chaſe 3. boates at once, which made their courſe with the ſound of trumpets from the Roſe bridge, rowing with great ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, paſſing vnder the Rawline: the firſt boate which came to the Caſtell wall on the ſide of <hi>Giude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> wan the price, which was of Red Crimſon Sattin, and therein were the women with Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: the other prize which was of Blew Sattin, was likewiſe won by thoſe in the Yellow and Blew. This ſhip chaſe was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected ſo prettyly and with ſuch paſtime, that euery one wondred at it, for theſe women plaide and ſung in thoſe boates, and daunced with great nimblenes.</p>
            <p>Hetherto haue I briefly ſet downe as much as I could know, there will not héereafter want other high ſpirits which with more circumſtance, and in ſome ſwéeter ſtile, will ſet forth at large what is happened.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20351:6"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
